Guide to the Alan Grob academic career records UA 413
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Alan Grob academic career records
1961-2007
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Grob, Alan, 1932-2007
UA 413
5 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
The Alan Grob academic career records offer insight into the teaching and personal life of Rice University professor of English Alan Grob. Containing a large number of his lecture notes in addition to his writings, university related documents, and documents such as correspondence, photographs, and news articles, the collection helps preserve the memory of his impact at Rice.
Biographical / Historical
Alan Grob was born on March 12, 1932 in New York City and died on September 21, 2007 in Houston, Texas. He was the much-loved son of Jack and Ida Grob. He received his B.A. from Utica College and his M.A. and PhD in English from the University of Wisconsin. He served as an officer in the U.S. Navy aboard the U.S.S. General W.A. Mann from 1953 to 1956. In 1961 he joined the Rice University English department, serving as chairman from 1981 to 1987. He received the George R. Brown Award for Superior Teaching five times and in 1973 he received Rice's highest teaching award, the George R. Brown Award for Excellence in Teaching. He was a visiting professor at Texas Southern University, the University of Indiana, and the University of the Saarland in West Germany, where he held both a Rotary and a Fulbright Fellowship.
As a specialist in 19th-century literature, Dr. Grob was the author of the books The Philosophic Mind: A Study of Wordsworth's Poetry and Thought, 1797-1805 and A Longing Like Despair: Arnold's Poetry of Pessimism, as well as many scholarly articles. Dr. Grob served as the president of the Wordsworth-Coleridge Association of America, as a member of the executive committee for the English Romantic Period section of the Modern Language Association from 1973 to 1977, and as chairman of that committee in 1976. He was a faculty associate at Hanszen College of Rice University from 1962 until his retirement in 2002.
A leading voice at Rice for social justice and for racial integration, Dr. Grob organized and chaired a faculty committee for minority recruitment in the early years of desegregation at Rice. Upon his retirement, former students and colleagues honored him by establishing the Alan Grob Prize to be awarded annually to the Rice undergraduate who, in the words of the donors, "has demonstrated the most devotion to the needs of the economically and culturally disadvantaged. The recipient's activities shall exemplify the values of community and service that Professor Grob lived and so eloquently sought to teach." In addition, in 2003 the Rice-TMS board established a scholarship for an incoming undergraduate minority student in Alan Grob's name.
Dr. Grob taught a highly popular course in Shakespeare for almost thirty years and in recognition of that very pleasurable association with the plays of Shakespeare he and his wife Shirley established the Alan and Shirley Grob Endowment for Shakespeare in Performance, a fund created to assist in bringing performances of the plays of Shakespeare to the Rice campus.
Dr. Grob loved being a teacher. He was deeply committed to sharing his enthusiasm for literature with the students he loved, and he prized his long friendships with many colleagues that he admired. He loved travel, particularly to the Lake District of England, politics, reading, following sports, and going out to dinner. Perhaps his favorite hobby was to participate in lively debates on subjects that stirred his interest. He took a keen interest in the lives of his children and their families and cherished the time he spent with them.
--Taken from Alan Grob's obituary in the Houston Chronicle
Scope and Contents
The collection contains teaching and class-related materials such as syllabi, lecture notes, course papers written by students, student evaluations of classes taught, and letters of recommendation for students. There are also materials pertaining to Rice University affairs, such as faculty records, papers about admissions and financial aid, president speeches, and texts and diary entries commenting on the Masterson Crisis. Also contained within the collection are writings by Alan Grob in the form of speeches, articles, and manuscripts for books he wrote, as well as personal items including correspondence, photographs, newsprint about his life, and awards he received. There are also a number of floppy disks containing backups of Alan Grob's computer disk and manuscripts for his book "Wordsworth and his Adversaries: A Study in the Hermeneutics of Disparagement."
The materials are in good condition and range in date from 1961 to 2007. Researchers interested in classes at Rice (particularly English Literature with a focus on Shakespeare, Victorian and Romantic writers, and Wordsworth), social and political shifts in the climate at Rice University, and the life and achievements of Alan Grob would find this collection helpful.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research. Restricted materials are marked in the finding aid.
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials were donated by Alan Grob's estate in 2020.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged in five series alphabetically or by date where possible, as below:
Series I: Teaching Materials; Series II: University Affairs; Series III: Writings and Manuscripts; Series IV: Personal; Series V: Floppy Disks
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges; Maps; Newspapers--Sections, columns, etc.; Education
Document Types
syllabi; lecture notes; papers (document genres); essays; letters (correspondence); Editorials; speeches; journals (accounts); manuscripts (document genre); photographs; obituaries; awards; floppy disks
Places
Rice University
- Series I: Teaching Materials
  - Syllabi for Grob courses (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Victorian Literature Syllabus (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lectures (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Humanities 102 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Sub-series A: Lecture Notes
    - Arnold (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Arnold (notes on scholarly texts) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Austen, "Emma" (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Austen, "Pride and Prejudice" (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Austen (Notes for teaching "Pride and Prejudice", "To the Lighthouse") (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Baudelaire, Charles: "The Flowers of Evil" (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Blake (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bronte, Charlotte: "Jane Eyre" (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Browning (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Byron (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Carlyle (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Cervantes, "Don Quixote" (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Chekhov & Carver (Stories) (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Coleridge (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Coleridge & Wordsworth: "Lyrical Ballads" (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - de Beauvoir (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Descartes (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Dostoevsky, Fyodor: "Crime and Punishment" (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Mircea Eliade (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - T. S. Eliot (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Existentialism (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Fitzgerald, Edward (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Flaubert (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Freud (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Frost (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Frye (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Goya (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Hardy, "Far from the Maddening Crowd" (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Hardy. "Jude the Obscure" (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Hardy, Thomas: "Mayor of Casterbridge" (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Hardy, Thomas: (Poetry) (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Hardy, Thomas: "Tess of the d'Urbervilles" (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Hopkins (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Kafka (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Kant (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Keats (1 of 5) (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Keats (2 of 5) (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Keats (3 of 5) (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Keats (4 of 5) (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Keats (5 of 5) (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - King Jr., Martin Luther (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Levi (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Literary Criticism (notes on reading texts) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Literary Theory (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Locke & Hume (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Machiavelli (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Mann (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Marquez (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Marx (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Michelangelo (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Mill (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Miller: "Death of a Salesman" (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Modern Drama (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Montaigne (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Mozart & Lorenzo da Ponte: "Marriage of Figaro" (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Nietzsche (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Northrup, "Twelve Years a Slave" (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Paine: "The Rights of Man" (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Picasso (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Plato (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Romantics (notes on scholarly texts 1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Romantics (notes on scholarly texts 2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Romantic Poetry (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Christina Rossetti (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Rousseau (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Ruskin (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Shakespeare (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Shakespeare (general) (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Shakespeare (introductory lecture) (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Shakespeare (notes for teaching, Byron) (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Sub-group A: Shakespeare
      - Antony and Cleopatra (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - As You Like It (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Coriolanus (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - Hamlet (Box 2, Folder 33)
      - Henry IV (Box 2, Folder 34)
      - Henry V (Box 2, Folder 35)
      - King Lear (Box 2, Folder 36)
      - Macbeth (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - Measure for Measure (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - Merchant of Venice (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 39)
      - Merchant of Venice (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 40)
      - A Midsummer Night's Dream (Box 2, Folder 41)
      - Othello (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Richard II (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Richard III (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Romeo and Juliet (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - The Tempest (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Twelfth Night (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Winter's Tale (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Shelley (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Sophocles: "Antigone" (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Stoppard, Tom: "Arcadia" (notes for teaching) (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Tennyson (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Tragedy (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Velasquez (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Victorian and Romantics (lecture notes) (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Victorian Novel (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Voltaire (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Woolf, Virginia, "To the Lighthouse: (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Wordsworth Criticism (1 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Wordsworth Criticism (2 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Wordsworth Criticism (3 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Wordsworth Lectures (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Wordsworth Notes on scholarly texts (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Wordsworth Notes (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Wordsworth on "Tintern Abbey" (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Wordsworth (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Wordsworth (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Sub-series B: Course papers
    - Class Rosters [Restricted], 2001, 2004-2006 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - British Romantic Poetry: exams and paper assignments (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Exams for Grob Courses (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Grade Books for Grob English Courses (1 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Grade Books for Grob English Courses (2 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Student Notebook from Grob's English 250 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Shakespeare course student papers (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Sub-series C: Student Evaluations
    - Student evaluations of English 339, Shakespeare, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Student evaluations of English 351, Romantic Poets, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Student evaluations of English 351, Romantic Poets, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Student Evaluations, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Student evaluations of English 211, Major British Writers 1800 to Present, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Sub-Series D: Letters of Recommendation
    - Letters of Recommendation, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Letters of Recommendation, 1984-1986 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Letters of recommendation, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Series II: University Affairs
  - Admissions and Financial Aid for freshmen, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - "Call to Conversation" from President Leebron (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Faculty Club Secretary Records, 1963-1965 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - The Masterson Crisis (texts by all parties involved), February, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Masterson Crisis diary entries for Donald Levin, 1969-02-20-1969-03-02 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Professor Office Map, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - University Welfare Committee, 1969-06-1969-12 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Series III: Writings and Manuscripts
  - Sub-series A: Speeches and Articles
    - Talks by Grob to diverse groups (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Education at Rice (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Faculty address given to freshmen (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - "Geography: The Invisible Preference" in Sallyport, Winter 1996, pp. 26-30 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - "Geography: The Invisible Preference" (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - High school seniors talk (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - "Invasion in Austin" in A.A.U.P. Bulletin, April 1975, pp. 5-12 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - "Invasion in Austin" and "Integration at Rice" (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - "Jewish identity: Reflections in Literature and Language" presentation (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Retirement event remarks (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Scholarly articles reprints (1 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Scholarly articles reprints (2 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Sub-series B: Manuscripts
    - Notes for Manuscript correction (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - "The Power and the Glory: Graham Green's Argument from Design" Manuscript (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - "Review of Contemporary Literary Theory" Manuscript (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - "Wordsworth and his Adversaries: A Study in the Hermeneutics of Disparagement" Manuscript related papers (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - "Wordsworth and his Adversaries: A Study in the Hermeneutics of Disparagement" Manuscript pp. 1-60 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - "Wordsworth and his Adversaries: A Study in the Hermeneutics of Disparagement" Manuscript pp. 72-85 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - "Wordsworth and his Adversaries: A Study in the Hermeneutics of Disparagement" Manuscript pp. 88-150 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - "Wordsworth and his Adversaries: A Study in the Hermeneutics of Disparagement" Manuscript pp. 147-282 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - "Wordsworth and his Adversaries: A Study in the Hermeneutics of Disparagement" Manuscript pp. 278-328 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - "Wordsworth and his Adversaries: A Study in the Hermeneutics of Disparagement" Manuscript pp. 278-341 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - "Wordsworth and his Adversaries: A Study in the Hermeneutics of Disparagement" Manuscript pp. 303-398 (Box 4, Folder 45)
- Series IV: Personal
  - Grob Fund for Shakespeare in Performance/Actors from the London Stage (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - T.S.U. Summer Institute (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Personal Address Book (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Personal Income notes [Restricted] (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Sub-series A: Correspondence
    - Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence: condolences (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Sub-group B: Photographs
    - Photo of Dr. Grob teaching a class (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Photo of Jay Grob in "Humanities at Rice" (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Sub-group C: Articles and Newsclippings about Alan Grob (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Newsclippings about Alan Grob (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Sallyport, Fall 1988 p. 14 photo and text about A. Grob (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - News article about 1993 matriculation address by Alan Grob (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Sallyport, Spring 2006, "Legacy of Beloved Teacher to Live on Through Performances of Shakespeare" (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Conditions for Retirement (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Recognition at Retirement (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Alan Grob Obituary Notices (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Tributes to Grob at the time of his death (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Sub-series D: Awards
    - Application for American Council of Learned Societies Fellowship (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Award from the Black Student Union of Rice University (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Hanszen College Outstanding Faculty Associate Award, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Hanszen College Outstanding Faculty Associate Award Certificate, 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Series V: Floppy Disks
  - Labeled as "LLD" [A Longing Like Despair] (8) (Box 5, Envelope 21)
  - Labeled as "W book" [Wordsworth and his Adversaries: A Study in the Hermeneutics of Disparagement] (8) (1 of 2) (Box 5, Envelope 22)
  - Labeled as "W book" [Wordsworth and his Adversaries: A Study in the Hermeneutics of Disparagement] (9) (2 of 2) (Box 5, Envelope 23)
  - Variously labeled including "Rec" (11) (Box 5, Envelope 24)
  - Hard Disk Copies (Box 5, Envelope 25)
  - Unlabeled disks (Box 5, Envelope 26)